so this is a question that's come up
recently from quite a few people
so I've just sort of paraphrased it into
one
so a friend asks the more I realized
that it's impossible for any of my
activities to be separate separate from
this body the nature of the body the
more I sense the confinement that pante
often mentions and the more oppressive
it feels
as a result I began to feel like
everything I do is worthless pointless
and you had self-loathing yeah sadness
yeah and this overwhelms me yeah I
believe that such thoughts
are rooted in ill will and a wish to
just give up just to
just to give up the practice and become
lazy I would appreciate it if you could
give me a few tips on how to go through
this kind of state yeah well by going
through it
so um
the self-loathing the worldlessness the
confinement that is yeah all factual
that is yeah all factual
but
the reason why it is painful
it's because your views your habits your
expectations are still kind of referred
to from the point of view of centrality
so the the central Pleasures the
ambition the inspiration
the spilling out in the world that is
still where your criterias are
habitually sure now you started
reflecting you saw no that that doesn't
add up it's actual confinement it sends
restraint all of that and now this is
felt unpleasant but it's felt
unpleasantly not because in and of
itself but it's felt unpleasantly
because you're still not fully abandoned
the previous kind of views and criterias
and Notions
so the self-loathing
aspect of of that confinement is due to
basically your
kind of addiction of sensuality still
being there and the only way to then for
that addiction to to sort of dissipate
is to endure the self-loading and don't
go back to sensuality they will then
revalue it re enthuse it again with the
old value
which would then remove the self-loading
from being immediately felt and put it
back into your framework as in sooner or
later when you don't have enough
sensuality you're going to go back and
you're going to start self-loading again
when the distractions sort of disappear
self-loathing is back confinement is
back so you you don't deal with it by doing
so you you don't deal with it by doing
this or that you deal with it by not
going back to centrality
and then the self-loading disappears
confinement remains as a factual thing
that it's not unpleasant anymore
and when the confinement remains no
other can exist outside of it
so if you go through the withdrawals and
endure the self-loading without a
Breaking the precepts without falling
back onto sensuality without
disregarding the training you will be
destroying the first three Fighters
but yeah the risk you might go mad if
you if you if you lose your restraint
if you um if you get overwhelmed and act
out you won't get mad if your mind is
just spinning out of control you get mad
by acting madly
so if you lose sense restraint and if
you don't guide your sense those that's
how you will then lose control not
otherwise in other words if you don't do anything
in other words if you don't do anything
on account of it it will have to come
down how long that takes well depends on how
how long that takes well depends on how
addicted you were before
but I reckon it would take a while
because we were all quite addicted
before if it weren't we would have been born in
if it weren't we would have been born in
the Buddhist time and become our Hand by
now is it
is it
you start yeah virtue Central streams
eventually you start feeling the
confinement that you are yeah in you're
feeling confined by the Aggregates
crushed which becomes very uninspiring
yeah there's nothing nothing we're doing yeah
there's nothing nothing we're doing yeah
exactly just pressure pressure just
enclosed yeah here I am enclosed this
so what do I do now
so well this paint it's just paint so
you just keep following that same
principle of that you've been that God
want to get rid of the pain yeah hmm
not trying to get rid of that pain
enduring it
yeah but again you can be enduring it
for the sake of getting it getting rid
of it
I'll endure this one it will go away
I'll endure it so it goes away oh yes
we have to so what do I do then
so I'm confined now
kind of sense restraint
nothing we're doing self-loading what do
I do next
what do you do
well Discerning the nature of that again
yeah okay yeah something else so what do
I do then
is there anything for me to do
why do you need to do this
because it's painful
confinement is unpleasant heroics
so why do I what do I do
it's painful because you want to do
something about it
no include that question in the pane
and I did and the paint's still here so
what do I do
well and keep and keep including it
they're keep including the wish to step
out and do something about it
other than God in the context as we said
many times and then what so if I include
the wish to step outside of it yes
now I can just relax and do stuff
because I included the wish yeah or do I
still not do certain things and do
certain things
no yeah sure do I like things to be
endured things to be different things to
be developed but no in this particular
example I'm confined
you're all giving me advice of what to
do
well you just don't it's what what is it
that I don't do break any precepts don't
act out exactly exactly you don't need
to do anything that's the point for as
long as what do I do next what do I do
next confinement will be confining even
more because you're trying to outrun it
so you do factually need to stop doing
certain things stop resisting that so
you can calm down but not too far
that's the the the right balance too
tight and too loose so if it's too much
I just can't bear it I can't even think
about it down anymore it's just so
unpleasant so painful so self-loading
what do I do nothing I just should not
go back to sensuality and distraction
everything else fine
I'll sit I'll walk I'll sleep
I'll talk you have something to say I
don't have to practice I won't practice
because it's too painful but I won't go
to sensuality I won't lose the sense
restraint and I will take down the
desired greed and distraction so what do
I do nothing just don't do literally
don't do anything which includes don't
go back to sensuality reason it isn't it
like you you're still doing that
discernment of this is unwholesome no
you won't be doing it
you can be doing it but the time will
come where even that cannot be sustained
you just have to give it up
it's just too painful
and what I'm saying is that we'll have
to come and when you give it up
give it up but not all the way because
you have not been doing certain things
you have been uh not you know breaking
the presets you have not been chasing
sensuality so now when you give up the practice as
so now when you give up the practice as
well
chasing sensuality and breaking the
precepts would be doing would be
requiring effort
yes and now that would also fall under
the principle no but I won't do anything
I won't practice I won't do anything
that exerts the effort because just the
thought of effort it just is just too
painful so okay fine you don't have to
make any effort when that point comes
just drop all the effort including
effort towards sensuality in Breaking
the precepts that you have been keeping
beforehand you know because as you just
said like you know chasing sensual
chasing sensuality requires effort and
maintenance yeah so that's a doing yeah
see if somebody before they have been
sufficiently withdrawn decides to drop
the effort because it's too painful well
sensuality is effortless for them
because they haven't been withdrawn from
it that's it yes so then when they drop
the effort they'll do the effortless
stuff which is pursue the sense desires
yeah so that's why the behavior as we
would say needs to be developed
beforehand the the purity of the body
Behavior so when that has been
sufficiently endured and you reach the
wall in terms of I can't even think
about a dhamma anymore it's just
unbearable fine
now just remember things that you have
not been doing and that's it
and you don't have to do anything new
just stay from abstaining from certain
things so that's effortless
and then whatever's there you are
Discerning it just not to an account of
your own intense terms out of trying to
get rid of the pain and so on
and actually yeah
you would see that even kind of giving
up in a sense that effort um
um
or even the like you know it's so
painful and I need to kind of keep
bearing in mind this pain or I keep like
what if I if I let it go then it might
be pleasant it might be peaceful it
might be okay and that's nearly in
itself kind of something to relinquish I
suppose the I the idea to kind of that
is you know I have to keep bearing the
pain yeah yeah because it might oh it
might change my Pleasant might be
painful oh okay
that's it doesn't have any open till anyway
it doesn't have any open till anyway
that's never in your control anyway but
they see you were trying to control it
in a sense even yeah well that's just
how the the Pains of striving work you
have to determine which means going to
result you're going to kind of overdo
the tightening because it was too loose
when things are too loose you don't just
magically stop right yeah in the right
tune no you're gonna be over tightening
it and then oh it's gonna snap now right
so let me loosen it but now you realize
okay let me loosen it but not as Lou
said as it was before
and that's how you will find the right
tune the right balance
but see when you are already tied to the
point of snapping and then what do I do
now whatever I tell you to do if it's done
whatever I tell you to do if it's done
on that on that on account of that
intention will be another twist for
tightening it
so what you do now is just nothing
oh so does that mean I go and break the
pieces well that's not nothing isn't it
so do nothing
so guys I'm sleepy I'm hungry I'll walk
I'll be silent
oh I'll go and distract aha now that's
too loose
okay I'll see the whole night and think
about them yeah it's too tight
so what I do now what do I do now
why do I need to know what do I do now
right here right now is that that
unpleasant and you realize then it was
only unpleasant because you kept trying
to sort of
get out of it but anyways well actually
I don't know what to do but that's not
that unpleasant I know what I will not
do and that's all I need to know
I don't need to know specific steps that
I need to do I just need to not forget
what I must not do and not doing things
is effortless
that's how you become an island to
yourself as well and that's how you
realize oh the line the line is the
action intentionally acting out of
things it's not this thought that though
this moment my moment sensation slept
for God
I'm sorry around no no
only if I intentionally choose to open
the door let the flood in that's how it
gets in if I don't do it doesn't matter
what's outside cannot flood me
intentions rooted in great diversion
distraction that's it
stain from those and don't do anything
else and you'll be fine